Hello friends welcome to the YouTube
channel of fencing where we are trying
to simplify the complicated world of
personal finance for you my name is
Raghu a certified financial planner by
qualification
in this video we will be sharing the
details of the health insurance policy
by ICICI Lombard called Health Advantage
policy
before we start let me give you a heads
up this is going to be a pretty long
video because we have made an effort to
explain the benefits of the policy in
detail and more importantly the
conditions in detail
most of the times insurance is purchased
by taking a quick look at the policy
benefits and not actually going through
the terms and conditions because of
which insured individuals often complain
about health insurance company not
honoring the claims my sincere request
to all of you is to see the video till
the end and in case of any questions
please share the same in the comment
section and we will do our best to
answer them for you
before we jump into the product features
let's look at some of the disclaimers
this video is meant for Education
purpose only you need to consult your
financial planner before proceeding with
any purchases
views expressed in this video are based
on our vast personal experience and
Analysis
we are associated with icsl embroid for
sales and Servicing
let first understand the need for health
insurance with the increasing pollution
stressful life popularity of junk food
lifestyle diseases like diabetes
cholesterol kidney and liver issues and
cardiac disorders have become quite
rampant we have seen quite a lot of
young people who are diagnosed with
these conditions
the cost of Health Care is on the rise
and so are the types of ailments
impacting us these days surgeries organ
transplants chemotherapy and such other
medical procedures can leave a massive
dent in your pocket having a sufficient
health insurance policy will come to
your rescue and take care of your
medical expenses so that you stay on
track in order to achieve your financial
goals
government of India also recognizes the
need for individuals to Avail medical
insurance and to encourage individuals
to Avail individual medical insurance
policies it provides certain tax reliefs
as well
for self and family below the age of 60
25 000 rupees can be deducted from
taxable income in case of senior citizen
same would be 50 000 rupees in addition
to this if an individual is availing the
medical insurance policy for parents
additional cover of 20K is available if
parents are below the age of 60 and 50
000 rupees if they are above the age of
60.
health insurance companies want you to
be healthy so that they don't have to
Shell out huge amount of money from
their pockets for medical expenses
in order to achieve that they provide
ancillary benefits like nutrition
consultations for weight loss discounts
if you exercise on a regular basis
yearly medical checkups
teleconsultations with doctors Etc
although this should not become the core
reason for you to buy the health
insurance it definitely works like a
cherry on top of the cake
let's now look at the benefit one can
Avail in this policy
some insured is the maximum amount of
money one can claim from the health
insurance company in return for the
premium which he or she is paying
individuals or families can take these
policies for some assured ranging from 5
lakh Rupees to 3 crores
inpatient care refers to all the
expenses incurred by the individual
while he or she is admitted in the
hospital as inpatient this policy
provides cover to the extent of the sum
insured that is for example if the
insurer has taken a policy of 10 lakh
Rupees and the hospital bill is around
10 lakh Rupees health insurance
companies liable to pay the entire Bill
except for certain non-medical items
which might account for hardly about
three to four percent of the bill amount
the boomerang plays an extremely
important role in claim settlement there
are policies which set a limitation on
the room rent and if an individual
avails a room where the rent is more
than the limit set by the insurance
company then the health insurance
company is liability to settle the bill
proportional to the room rent
let me explain this with an example
let's assume the room rent upper limit
is 4000 rupees per day as per the policy
and if the insured has opted for a room
rent costing 5000 rupees per day
mathematically health insurance is
obligated to cover only 80 percent of
the total cost that is 4000 divided by
5000 multiplied by 100. at the time of
the discharge total hospitalization Bill
if it amounts to about 5 lakh rupees in
this situation health insurance company
will settle the bill using the simple
formula 5 lakh divided by 5000
multiplied by 4000 rupees which amounts
to about 4 lakh rupees fortunately this
policy does not have any room rent
capping so one need not worry about the
category of the room to Avail
guaranteed cumulative bonus or GCB is an
excellent feature in this policy if no
claim has been made in a policy Year by
the insured then for each such policy
year the company will offer a GCB of 20
percent of some insured maximum up till
hundred percent of some insured let's
understand this with an example of an
individual who has taken a health
insurance policy with 5 lakh rupees as
some ensured
in case of no claim on year 0 after the
first year renewal insured will be
eligible for 20 of 5 lakh rupees
that's one lack of GCB and the total sum
insured increases to 6 lakhs
Year One
let's assume also had no claims
additional 1 lakh of GCB was added and
the total sum insured became 7 lakh
rupees
year two had a claim so no GCB was added
at the same time the total sum assured
will not go down as well and Remains the
Same as 7 lakh this is where GCB differs
from no claim bonus where the sum
insured reduces during the clean year
another example for year three let's
assume it also had a claim so no GCB
this time as well and the sun insured
remains as 7 lakh
in addition to the modern medicines
insured can also opt for ayurveda unani
siddha and Homeopathy treatments
commonly known as ayush up to some
insured there are few conditions which
are applicable here one this will be on
reimbursement basis only and cashless
hospitalization is not available
when the insured requires an organ
donation this policy will cover the
hospitalization expenses incurred for
harvesting the donated organ up to some
insured it will also cover screening
expenses of the donor if he or she is
accepted as donor
post donation fitness test certificate
this also covers any medical expenses as
a result of complications arising
because of harvesting from the donor
but it should be either before six
months of organ harvesting or before the
end of the policy whichever is earlier
any medical expenses incurred 60 days
prior to hospitalization is also covered
similarly any medical expenses incurred
180 days after the insurance admission
to the hospital will also be covered in
the policy
maximum amount which one can claim under
this Clause is limited to the sum
insured and it is available only on
reimbursement basis and it won't be
cashless
with the advancement in the field of
Medical Science most of the procedures
which used to require 24 hours of
hospitalization are now treated without
hospitalization
this policy also covers all the daycare
procedures required
this policy also provides restore
benefit
this is called by different insurers
with different names like reset rebound
or restore
under this policy if the insurer has
completely utilized the sum insured and
GCB during a policy year and if the
insured needs to incur additional
medical expenses again for any ailment
accident or injury which is a valid
admissible claim then the insurance
company restores hundred percent of the
original sum insured of the policy and
the same is called as regained some
insured
usually this restore benefit is
available for non-related ailments that
is ailments for which claim was not paid
earlier however this policy covers event
related ailments
this restore benefit is available just
once in a policy year and this is
restored even on account of partial or
full utilization of summon short
if the regained some insured is not
utilized in a policy year it cannot be
carried forwarded to the next year
this policy provides reimbursement of
one percent of some insured up to a
maximum of 10 000 Rupees to cover
medical expenses of opt treatment for
vaccination or humanization for treating
animal bites
nowadays most of the insurance providers
support the domiciliary hospitalization
as well let's understand what
domiciliary hospitalization is
any medical treatment required for
illness disease or injury which under
normal circumstances is treated in the
hospital however if the same is taken
from home it's called a mercillary
hospitalization it also covers expenses
on qualified nurses engaged on the
recommendation of the attending medical
practitioner however we need to note
that this comes with few conditions
patients should not be in a position to
be moved to a hospital or it should be
on account of non-availability of a room
in a hospital
the treatment which is taken under this
feature shouldn't be for a period of
more than three days
anything less than three days is not
going to be supported in this policy
bariatric surgery is required when an
individual is unable to lose weight with
exercise and diet and the doctors advise
for a surgery to control the overweight
issue this policy will cover reasonable
amount of expenses associated with this
procedure subject to 50 of the sum
insured with a maximum cap of 10 lakh
Rupees and one can Avail this after
having a waiting period of three years
some of the conditions which needs to be
fulfilled
or inserts should be 18 years or older
with a BMI of 40 or more and in
conjunction with severe comorbidities
like coronary heart disease or medically
refractory hypertension or type 2
diabetes
two qualified surgeons should certify
that this procedure is actually required
and rare approval from the health
insurance company is a must
if these conditions are not met health
insurance company can deny the claims
towards bariatric surgery
on an annual basis up to 0.5 percent of
the sum insured subject to a maximum of
10 000 rupees can be claimed for health
checker on cashless basis for
individuals above the age of 18.
convalescence benefit is a cash paid to
the insured person if he or she is
hospitalized for a period of more than
10 days and the claim is accepted by the
insurance company for the same this can
be claimed once in a policy year this
amount is paid over and above some
insured
worldwide cover is available under this
policy if they insured opts for a cover
of 215 lakh rupees or more this is
available on reimbursement basis only
with the exchange rate published by RBI
on the date of loss a co-payment of 10
is applicable for all the claims this
covers the inpatient and Day Care
procedures however pre and post
hospitalization claims are not allowed
under this benefit
this policy also covers expenses
incurred for surface ambulance on
cashless and reimbursement basis to the
extent of one percent of some assured up
to a maximum of 10 000 rupees per
hospitalization
there are few more optional benefits
which are built into the policy let's
review some of them by paying an
additional premium one can Avail
domestic air ambulance facility also
under this policy up to policy some
insured however these are subject to few
conditions
it should be for life-threatening
emergency health conditions of the
insured and transportation would be
limited to the nearest hospital for
medical treatment and transportation
should be certified in writing
biomedical practitioner and Road
ambulance services should not be
available
air ambulance or provider should process
the valid license for operating air
ambulance
treatment taken at the hospital should
be a valid claim payable by the
insurance company
air ambulance available for transporting
insured from One hospital to another or
hospital to residents of insured or
facility availd outside of India or not
covered under this policy
ambulance assistance is an additional
paid service provided by the insured for
ground transportation
daily consultations this is one of the
most amazing benefits available under
this policy wherein the insured can
raise a request for teleconsultation
with a medical professional through the
icsa Lombard mobile app
and a call with a medical professional
will be arranged after listening to the
medical issues medical professional will
prescribe the medication required
my family has utilized this facility
during covet times When approaching the
hospitals was risky and even now for
certain medical issues we seek tele
consultation this facility is available
absolutely free of charge
Home Care treatment cover provides for
cashless treatment of medical expenses
incurred by the insured on home
treatment up to five percent of some
insured subject to a maximum of 25 000
rupees this is acceptable only if the
medical practitioner has advised to
undergo such treatment at home
treatments that can be availed on opt
basis or out of scope of this benefit
in addition to the earlier discussed
options
there are few more optional benefits one
can Avail by paying additional premiums
for example women aged between 18 and 45
they can opt for maternity benefits
wherein the insured company or insured
policy will cover up to three deliveries
to the extent of 10 percent of the sum
insured subject to maximum of 10 lakh
Rupees this covers the expenses
associated with the delivery of the baby
and also covers expenses related to the
medically recommended legal termination
of pregnancy but only in life
threatening situation under the advice
of a medical practitioner
is it as simple as it looks definitely
no let's look at the conditions
associated with it while availing the
policy insured should take the cover for
three years in one go
insurance premium with maternity cover
would be a bit higher than the premium
for the base insurance coverage example
for a couple in the late 20s if they are
opting for an insurance cover of 10 lakh
Rupees
for um and cover of three years without
maturity they will have to pay around 53
000 rupees as premium
same with maternity cover the premium
for three years changes to 1.77 lakhs a
difference of almost about 1.25 lakh
you cannot claim the benefit immediately
after taking in the policy there is a
waiting period of nine months
delivery date should be after nine
months from the date of taking the
policy
ectopic pregnancy is a type of pregnancy
in which the fetus develops outside the
uterus
typically in a fallopian tube and the
same is not covered under this benefit
when you opt for the maternity cover new
baby cover also will be a part of the
benefit wherein in case of
hospitalization of baby health insurance
company will provide twice the maternity
cover for the newborn
important point to note
here is that this cover is over and
above the maternity limit
newborn babies vaccination cost up to
one percent of the sum insured or rupees
10 000 whichever is lower will also be
covered under this policy this is over
and above the maternity cover to claim
this benefit health insurance companies
should have accepted the maternity claim
Riders are additional benefits which the
insured can get by paying additional
premium
there are two Riders which one can opt
for
first one is the claim protector
under a normal health insurance policy
there is a list of excluded items
released by irdai which is not covered
and paid by the health insurance policy
usually this accounts for about three to
four percent of the overall Bill
generated by the hospital
however adding this claim protector
Rider in this policy will ensure that
the bills associated for these excluded
items are also settled during the claim
settlement process
you might want to pause the video for a
couple of minutes to go through the list
of excluded items not covered under
normal hospitalization cover which is
displayed on the screen
inflation is a silent monster which
erodes the value of money over time
it's important for us to increase our
sum insured on a regular basis to tackle
the effect of inflation
this radar some insured protector helps
us in increasing the sum insured on an
annual basis based on the Consumer Price
Index data which is published by Central
statistical organization
we should note that the increase would
be only on the sum insured and not on
the GCB
if you're finding the information useful
please subscribe to our Channel like
this video and share it with your
friends and family
now that we have seen the policy
benefits it's equally important for us
to take a look into the permanent
exclusions to understand what are not
covered in the policy
concept of insurance has originated from
the idea of loss of few being reimbursed
by the small amount of treatments
collected by collected from a large
group of individuals
in conditions like War nuclear chemical
or biological attack number of people
impacted would be significantly higher
and this would drive the insurance
provider to bankruptcy
because of this reason all medical
expenses associated with war nuclear
chemical or biological attacks are not
covered in this policy this is the case
with all the other insurance providers
as well
any treatment taken outside the country
for policies where the sum insured is
less than 25 lakhs are also not covered
under this policy
if the insured has taken admission in
the hospital primarily for diagnosis and
evaluation purposes they are also not
covered also any diagnostic expenses
which are not related to or not
incidental to the current diagnosis and
treatment they are also excluded from
this policy benefit
expenses related to any admission
primarily for enforced bed rest and not
for receiving treatment
this also includes any custodial care
either at home or in a nursing facility
for personal care such as health with
activities of daily living such as
bathing dressing moving around either by
skilled persons and nurses or assistant
or non-skilled persons any services for
people who are terminally ill to address
physical social emotional and spiritual
needs are also not covered under this
policy
expenses related to the surgical
treatment of obesity that does not
fulfill the following conditions are
also not covered
one surgery has to be conducted upon the
advice of the doctor two surgery or the
procedure conducted should be supported
by clinical protocols
the member of undergoing the surgery
should be 18 years of age or older
fourth body mass index
should be greater than or equal to 40 or
it should be greater than or equal to 35
in conjunction with any of the following
severe comorbidities
one obesity related cardiomyopathy two
coronary heart disease three severe
sleep apnea four uncontrolled type 2
diabetes
expenses related to any treatment
including surgical management to change
characteristics of the body to those of
the opposite sex is not covered
expenses for cosmetic or plastic surgery
or any treatment to change appearance is
not covered unless for reconstruction
following an accident burn or cancer or
as part of medically necessary treatment
to remove a direct and immediate health
risk to the insured for this to be
considered a medical necessity it must
be certified by the attending medical
practitioner
expenses related to any treatment
necessitated due to participation as a
professional in hazardous or adventure
sports including but not limited to para
jumping rock climbing mountaineering
rafting motor racing horse racing or
scuba diving and gliding skydiving deep
sea diving all of them would not be
covered and under this policy
expenses for treatment directly arising
from or consequent upon any insured
person committing or attempting to
commit a breach of law with Criminal
Intent is also not covered example fall
from a high-rise building while
attempting to rob a house
expenses incurred towards treatment in
any hospital or by any medical
practitioner or any others provide a
specifically excluded by the insurer and
disclosed in its website notified to the
public policyholders are not admissible
however in case of life-threatening
situations or following an accident
expenses up to the stage of
stabilization are payable but not the
complete claim
any treatment for alcoholism drug or
substance abuse or any other addictive
condition and consequences thereof are
not going to be covered under this
policy
any treatment received in health hydros
nature Q clinics spas or similar
establishments or private beds
registered as a nursing home attached to
such establishments or where admission
is arranged whole year partly for
domestic reasons won't be covered
dietary supplements and substances that
can be purchased without prescription
including but not limited to vitamins
minerals and organic substances unless
prescribed by a medical practitioner as
part of hospitalization claim or Day
Care procedures would also not be
covered
any expense related the treatment for
correction of eyesight due to refractive
error less than 7.5 direct address will
not be covered expenses related to any
unproven treatment services and supplies
for or in connection with any treatment
will also not be covered unproven
treatments or treatments or procedures
or supplies that lack significant
medical documentation to support their
effectiveness
any expense incurred towards sterility
and infertility will also not be covered
this includes any type of contraception
or sterilization
assisted reproduction services including
artificial insemination and advanced
reproductive Technologies such as IVF
zift
gifft icsi will also not be covered
gestational surrogancy and reversal of
sterilization is also not covered under
this policy
any medical treatment expenses traceable
to childbirth that's including
complicated deliveries and cesarean
sections incurred during hospitalization
except ectopic pregnancy will not be
covered expenses towards miscarriage
unless due to an accident and lawful
medical termination of pregnancy during
the policy period
if the insured has opted for medical or
sorry if the insured has opted for
maternity cover then the provisions of
maternity cover will be applicable
any expense incurred on OPD treatment
would be out of scope from this policy
benefit
in addiction to the earlier listed
permanent exclusions this is illness or
ailments
this slide also contains the list of all
the ailments which are not going to be
covered in the first two years of the
policy you might want to pause the video
for a minute to go through the list
now that we have understood the policy
benefits conditions and exclusions let's
understand who all can Avail this policy
minimum entry age of the insured should
be 91 days and maximum should be 65.
any dependent child who does not have an
independent source of income and up to
the age of 25 can be covered under this
family floater option
this policy can be renewed till lifelong
for adults however any dependent child
will be dropped from the policy cover
after attaining the age of 20. this
policy can be both for individuals as
well as family also individuals entities
with insurable interest can purchase the
policy for individuals like employer
acting as proposal for employees and
their family members definition of
family here means grandfather
grandmother father-in-law mother-in-law
father mother spouse son daughter
son-in-law daughter-in-law grandson
granddaughter brother sister
sister-in-law and brother-in-law
as discussed earlier there are waiting
periods for availing benefits under this
policy
insured cannot Avail a hospitalization
benefit during the first 30 days of the
policy unless the hospitalization is on
account of an accident
any pre-existing diseases which the
insured has declared while availing the
policy would be covered after two years
of renewal that's from the third year
onwards
specific conditions which we have listed
earlier will be covered after two years
of relieval once again from the third
year onwards Bariatric Treatment can be
avoid after three years of renewal
as the medical expenses which an
individual incurs varies depending upon
the insurance location premium for the
insured in this policy is charged based
on the place of residence
and three zones have been fixed by the
insurance company which is displayed on
the screen this can be upgraded based on
insurance convenience if an individual
has opted for Zone 1 he or she can go
for hospitalization in any of the zones
without any co-payment
if the insured from Zone 2 wants to
Avail hospitalization in zone 1 then
there will be a co-payment of 12.5
percent there won't be any co-payment
for treatment taken in zone 3. if an
insert from Zone 3 wants to Avail
hospitalization in zone 1 then there
will be a co-payment of 15 percent same
stands for 12.5 percent in case of Zone
2.
as per irdi guidelines all medical
insurances have a free look period of 15
days from the date of receipt of the
policy so that the insurer can go
through the policy terms and conditions
in detail
this is available only on new policies
and not available for renewals or at the
time of porting or migrating the policy
if the insured decides to return the
health insurance policy within this
period premium paid by him or her would
be returned after deducting any expenses
which would have been incurred towards
medical expenses like medical checkup
stamp Duty charges or proportionate risk
premium for the period of cover
at the time of policy renewal insured is
given a grace period of 30 days for
annual premium policies and 15 days for
other than annual premium policies for
renewing the policy after the expiry of
the policy period
who doesn't like discount if the insurer
is purchasing the policy for two years
insured can Avail a discount of 7.5
percent on the total premium and in case
of three years it stands at 10 percent
in addition to the discount when the
insure takes the insurance for multiple
years he or she can be assured of no
price hikes for the following policy
period
after the free lookup period if the
insurer wants to cancel or terminate the
policy health insurance company will
retain a certain percentage of Premium
based on the number of months expired
from the date of policy issuance and
reimburses the rest you can refer the
table on the screen for one year
here is a table for policies purchased
for two years
on the screen you can see the table for
policies purchased for three years
let's now look at the most important
aspect that's how to get our claims
processed on cashless basis
as soon as we get the policy document we
should check out for the network
hospitals where one resides
and during the health emergencies one
should look for getting admission in one
of these Network hospitals you can also
find the list of network hospitals from
the company website
during emergency one can get admitted
and then reach out to the insurance desk
of the hospital to submit the relevant
documents for authorization
however if its planned hospitalization
it's advisable to approach the insurance
desk two to three days prior to
admission and submit the documents for
approval process
Insurance risk of the hospital will
forward the documents to the icacl
Lombard Healthcare team for approval
in case of no queries icsa Lombard
Healthcare team will provide the
authorization and in case of any query
will ask for additional documentation
if the hospitalization is on account of
any exclusions listed in the policy icsa
Lombard Healthcare team can also reject
the claim
it's not always possible to get treated
in the network hospitals and Avail the
cashless benefit sometimes insured might
have to be treated in non-network
hospitals and at that time insured needs
to pay the hospital bills and then
submit the claim with the health
insurance company
incurred need to pay all the hospital
bills upon discharge and collect all the
original bills and reports of the
procedures and event
then insured will have to submit a claim
form to the health insurance company
along with all the original bills
in case of no queries icsa Lombard care
team will provide the authorization for
payment and in case of a query we'll ask
for additional documentation
if the hospitalization is on account of
any exclusions listed in the policy
icaclombard Healthcare team can reject
the claim
all claims approved by the ICICI Lombard
Healthcare team will be settled to the
insurance bank account
we hope you found this video useful you
can always reach out to us for a free
consultation to have your queries
addressed
we can be contacted by either phone or
email ID displayed on the screen
if you like this video request you to
subscribe to our Channel like this video
and share it with your friends and
family
see you in our next video thank you